(upbeat music)
- Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- My name is Katherine.
And today we have an
intermediate level lesson
all about a very special kind of
person who helps you out with your kids.
- That's right, today we
want to get a nanny, a nanny.
- And nanny.
So a nanny is a person, usually a woman,
but it can be a man as well, I guess.
And this person takes care of your children
when you're working or
when you're out of the house.
- That's right.
- So this is what's going on today.
We're gonna see what type
of responsibilities a nanny has.
And so let's listen to a dialogue
and we'll be back in a bit.
(gentle music)
- Hey Lydia, what are you reading?
- I'm looking at my
horoscope for this month.
My outlook is very positive.
It says that I should take a
vacation to some place exotic
and that I will have a
passionate summer fling.
- What are you talking about?
- Let me see that.
What are horoscopes?
- It's a prediction of your
month based on your zodiac sign.
You have a different sign for the
month and date you were born in.
I was born on April 15th, so I'm an Aries.
When were you born?
- January 5th.
- Let's see.
You're a Capricorn.
It says that you'll be
feeling stress at work,
but you could see new, exciting
developments in your love life.
Looks like we'll both
have interesting summers.
- That's bogus.
I don't feel any stress at work and
my love life is practically non-existent.
This zodiac stuff is all
a bunch of nonsense.
- No, it's not.
Your astrology sign can tell
you a lot about your personality.
- See, it says that an Aries is
energetic and loves to socialize.
- Well, you certainly match those criteria,
but they're so broad they
could apply to anyone.
What does it say about me?
- A Capricorn is
serious-minded and practical.
She likes to do things
in conventional ways.
- That sounds just like you.
All right, we're back.
So now, let's take a look at some
key words on language takeaway.
- Language takeaway.
So as you said, Marco,
we don't just find an Annie.
We hire an Annie.
So what is the word hire a meme?
- Okay, so we have the
verb to hire someone,
and that means to get
someone to work for you, and you
pay them obviously money
in exchange for their services.
- Okay, so this is different
from finding a job for someone,
because I could find a job for someone,
but maybe that job is at a restaurant.
But when I hire someone,
that means I want
that person to work
for me, for my company.
- That's right.
So in this case, obviously,
we are not a company.
We are just a couple of people
who are looking for an Annie.
So we need to hire an Annie.
We need to get her to work for us,
and obviously you will pay her a salary.
- All right, so when you pay her a salary,
you also have some expectations
about what the Nanny will do.
So one of those
expectations is that the Nanny
will take the children to
their after-school activities.
- That's right, so this
is a phrase, if you will,
or a type of thing that
happens after school.
So usually children, when
they finish their classes,
they have some things that they can
do at school, like, for example, sports.
- That's right, so this is
very common in America,
but not so common in
other parts of the world.
So just to explain, if
your child is in high
school or middle school,
after school is over,
there's no more class, your child might
want to play soccer, or to go to art class.
And these are things
that you do at the school,
but it's usually considered
an activity, not a class.
And so we call these
after-school activities.
- That's right, so these activities
are usually for recreation.
They're not really part of the curriculum.
It's not a class.
- No, you don't get
marks or grades for these.
These are just for fun,
a lot of people work.
And so they need to have
these activities for their
kids to stay at school
until they finish working.
- That's right.
Okay, so we want the
nanny to take the children
or pick them up from
their after-school activities.
And we also need the nanny to
help out with some household chores.
- Okay, so you should
know where these chores
are being done, the first word is
household, which means in the house.
- Okay, so examples of household chores
would be like cleaning the windows,
washing the dishes, or doing laundry.
So basically any type of
cleaning around the house.
- That's right, making
the house look nicer.
And so usually children have chores.
These are things they need to do, but a
nanny can also help with household chores.
- Okay, and also we want the
nanny to help and run some errands.
- Okay, so this is funny, this phrasal
verb, this phrase uses the word to run.
But we're not running like a sport.
We're going to do some errands,
but the verb here is to run errands.
So Marco on Sunday, I
have to run some errands.
I'm sorry I can't go out to
the movie with you guys.
- Okay, so to run errands,
what does that mean?
- Well, an errand is like a job or a task
that you have to do, but
it's usually not something
you get paid for to do to run an
errand is like to go to the grocery store
and pick up food or to pick up your clothes
at the laundry mat, you have dry cleaning.
- Okay, so they're kind
of like chores, I guess,
but you don't really
do them in the house.
You have to go outside
and run these errands.
You have to go pay your bills, for example.
- Exactly, and so when I was growing up, on
the weekends, my mother would always run
all of her errands because
during the week, she had to work.
- Okay, very good.
So a lot of interesting words there,
I think we can go ahead and
listen to the dialogue again
and we'll be back in
a bit with Fluentibular.
(gentle music)
- Hey, Lydia, what are you reading?
- I'm looking at my
horoscope for this month.
My outlook is very positive.
It says that I should take a vacation
to someplace exotic and that I
will have a passionate summer fling.
- What are you talking about?
- Let me see that, what are horoscopes?
- It's a prediction of your
month based on your zodiac sign.
You have a different sign for the
month and date you were born in.
I was born on April 15th, so I'm an Aries.
When were you born?
- January 5th.
- Let's see, you're a Capricorn.
It says that you'll be
feeling stress at work,
but you could see new, exciting
developments in your love life.
Looks like we'll both
have interesting summers.
- That's bogus.
I don't feel any stress at work, and
my love life is practically non-existent.
This zodiac stuff is all
a bunch of nonsense.
- No, it's not.
Your astrology sign can tell
you a lot about your personality.
See, it says that an Aries is
energetic and loves to socialize.
- Well, you certainly match those criteria,
but they're so broad they
could apply to anyone.
What does it say about me?
- A Capricorn is
serious-minded and practical.
She likes to do things
in conventional ways.
Capricorn sounds just like you.
All right, we're back with Fluency Builder,
and so let's take a look at
some of these phrases now.
Fluency Builder.
- So this first phrase is a
very spoken English phrase,
something that you're
going to hear all the time,
especially if you're talking
to your American friends,
we say, "Are you up for some
tennis today to be up for?
" - Okay, so to be
up for something,
this is from the very first
sentence when Grace says,
"Hey, Mel, are you up
for some tennis today?
" What does it mean if I ask
someone if they are up for some tennis?
- This means, would you
like to play tennis today?
Are you interested in playing tennis today?
So is this a good idea for you?
Do you want to do this?
- So basically, are you
willing to play tennis today?
- Yes.
All right, so to be up
for is to be interested in
or willing to do something,
are you up for a movie tonight?
- All right.
- Or maybe you can ask your friend, are
you up for grabbing a bite to eat later on?
- So literally, I'm hungry.
So to be up for is a good
way to ask a question.
After that though, we have another phrase.
This phrase is very important when
you're trying to get someone to help you.
So how do we ask, can you help me?
- In the dialogue, we saw how Mel said that
it would be a great idea to get a nanny
because she would love to
have someone to help me out.
So to help someone out, to help me out.
- So this is interesting
because you could say,
I need someone to help me, but it's more
common to hear the phrase to help me out.
So you're not going out.
You're not, it doesn't
have to do with space,
but we just say this phrase to
help out means to help someone.
- So it's basically the exact same thing,
but it just sounds a lot more natural.
- Exactly, so Marco, I'm moving tomorrow.
Do you have some time to help me out?
- Okay, so you say help me out, but you
could also say, do you have time to help me?
- Exactly. - Both are okay.
Or if I'm talking about me and my
friend, we're really busy tomorrow.
Do you have any time to help us out?
- Okay, so we just changed the
person there, we went to the plural form.
- Yes, me, us, you.
- Okay, very good.
Okay, and so for our last phrase,
this is actually also very interesting
when Grace was telling Mel that
she's really busy and if she gets a nanny,
she wouldn't have to
juggle such a busy schedule.
- All right, so the key
verb here is to juggle.
Now, I wish I could show this to you guys,
but as this is an audio podcast, I can't.
What is the verb to juggle me Marco?
- Well, I don't know if
you've ever seen clowns
or at a circus where
people have three balls
and they throw them
in the air with two hands
and they're basically
throwing stuff in the air,
sometimes balls or
pins and stuff like that.
- Sometimes fire.
- Fire, so that's to juggle,
basically to have many things
in your hands and be able to
move them at the same time.
- All right, so when you're
talking about a busy schedule,
this means that you have
lots and lots of things to do.
It's important to be able to
juggle your busy schedule.
That means to handle doing
many things at the same time.
- That's right, that's right.
- So another way to
say this is because you're
so busy right now, having
a nanny will help you
complete your tasks or
finish what you need to do.
- That's right, so you can also say the CEO
of the company has to
juggle a very busy schedule.
- All right, he has many,
many things to do in general.
- That's right, okay.
So a lot of stuff, I think it's time for us
to listen to this dialogue one last time
and we'll be back to
talk a little bit more.
(gentle music)
- Hey, Lydia, what are you reading?
- I'm looking at my
horoscope for this month.
My outlook is very positive.
It says that I should take a
vacation to someplace exotic
and that I will have a
passionate summer fling.
- What are you talking about?
Let me see that.
What are horoscopes?
- It's a prediction of your
month based on your zodiac sign.
You have a different sign for the
month and date you were born in.
I was born on April 15th, so I'm in Aries.
When were you born?
- January 5th.
- Let's see, you're a Capricorn.
It says that you will be
feeling stress at work,
but you could see new, exciting
developments in your love life.
Looks like we'll both
have interesting summers.
- That's bogus.
I don't feel any stress at work and
my love life is practically non-existent.
This zodiac stuff is all
a bunch of nonsense.
- No, it's not.
Your astrology sign can tell
you a lot about your personality.
See, it says that an Aries is
energetic and loves to socialize.
- Well, you certainly match those criteria,
but they're so broad,
they could apply to anyone.
What does it say about me?
- A Capricorn is
serious-minded and practical.
She likes to do things
in conventional ways.
That sounds just like you.
(gentle music)
So there are a lot of people all
over the world who have nannies.
I often see them when
I go to New York City.
You know, women who take out
the kids and they push them in strollers
and mom and dad may be good at
work or have classes or something.
- That's right.
Now, this is interesting
because there's also another word
called a babysitter,
but it's different, right?
There's a difference between
a nanny and a babysitter.
They both take care of kids, but I
think it's the time that they do it.
It's a difference.
- That's right.
So a nanny is usually hired
on like a contract basis.
You say, I need a nanny
to come and watch my kids
every day, Monday to
Friday for the next six months.
But with a babysitter,
you say, hey, my husband
and I, we want to go to
watch a movie on Friday.
Can you come for two hours?
- Okay.
- All right, so a nanny is long-term.
It's someone who maybe lives with you.
Someone who does some work at your house,
someone who cleans the
dishes and watches the kids.
But a babysitter just comes, you know,
once a month or just when you need her.
- That's right.
Okay.
So that's the main difference
between a nanny and a babysitter now.
As you said, they're very,
very common nowadays
because I guess it's not like
before when women usually
would stay at home and
take care of the children.
Now both parents usually work.
And so more people are getting nannies.
- That's right.
Although nannies can be very
expensive, it depends where you live.
And so for people who can't
afford a nanny, you know, if a
nanny is too expensive, the
child, the baby, will go to daycare.
And that's actually like a place where
many babies or children are together.
And there's, you know, one teacher or one
or one nanny and takes care of everyone.
- That's right.
So it's an interesting topic.
Maybe some of our
listeners grew up with a nanny
or had a nanny when they
were growing up or maybe
you have kids of your own
and you have a nanny now.
- Yeah, let us know.
You should check our website out.
We are EnglishPod.com.
We hope to see you guys there.
- Okay, bye. - Bye.
(upbeat music)